｢There was a hungry crow｣
♪ ｢お 腹 空 かせた ｶﾗｽがいた｣
｢who somewhow wanted to get some feed｣
♪ ｢なんとか 餌 に ありつきたい｣
｢if this beak was only longer｣
♪ ｢この くちばしが もっと長ければ｣
｢that feed would be a bit closer｣
♪ ｢あの餌が もっと こっちに来れば｣
♪ ～
♪ ～
｢a crow can think｣
｢ｶﾗｽは考える ｶﾗｽは考える ｶﾗｽは考える ｶﾗｽは考える｣
｢can think... can think｣
♪ ｢考える 考える｣
Observe, propose a hypothesis, test and consider.
観察し 仮説を立て 実験をし 考察する｡
Learn the method of scientific thought.
科学の考え方を学べ｡
We start with a ｢Thinking Observation｣.
まずは ｢考える観察｣から｡
Observing a one yen piece floating in water.
今日は 水に 浮 かぶ一円玉を 観察してみる｡
If we push it to the edge...
端 に寄せても →
It returns to its position.
戻 ってくる｡
Even if we push it to a different position...
別の所に寄せても… →
it returns.
戻ってくる｡
Let's try adding a peice of wood.
試しに 木片 をのせてみる｡
It sticks to the edge.
端に くっついた｡
Even if we move it away...
離 しても…｡
It again sticks to the edge.
また 端に くっつく｡
Let's try adding another one yen piece.
もう一枚 一円玉をのせてみる｡
It sticks to its comrade.
一円玉同士が くっついた｡
And even if we separate them...
離しても…｡
they stick.
くっつく｡
Let's try adding some water.
水を足してみる｡
♪ ～
♪ ～
The one yen pieces move to the rim, and the wooden block comes the center.
一円玉が端に寄って 木片が真ん中に来た｡
It's reversed.
逆になった｡
Even if we move the wooden block to the edge...
木片を端に寄せても…｡
It comes back.
戻ってくる｡
Even if we peel a yen from the edge...
一円玉を端から 剥 がしても →
on its own it sticks to the edge again.
勝手に 端に くっつく｡
Let's try removing some water.
水を 抜 いてみる｡
It returns to the original state.
元に戻った｡
Is there some difference between the yen piece and the block?
一円玉と木片 何が そんなに 違 うのか｡
｢Thinking Observation｣.
｢考える観察｣｡
♪ ～
♪ ～
Today our problem deals with a platter and a baloon.
今日は お 盆 と風船を使った 問題です｡
I let go of the platter and the balloon at the same time.
お盆と風船 同時に手を離します｡
The platter falls first. the baloon falls later, more slowly.
お盆が先に落ちて 風船は 後から ゆっくり落ちます｡
Now this is the problem.
ここからが問題です｡
This time I put the balloon on top of the platter.
今度は お盆の上に 風船をのせます｡
And then let go.
そして 手を離すと →
What will happen to the platter and baloon?
この お盆と風船は どうなるでしょうか？
We'll reveal the answer at the end of the program.
答えは 番組の最後で発表します｡
Everyone, you'll think about it won't you?
皆 さん 考えておいて下さいね｡
♪ ～
♪ ～
And now, the answer.
では 先ほどの答えです｡
Did everyone think about it carefully?
皆さん ちゃんと考えましたか？
Okay. Let's do it.
では やってみましょう｡
How will the platter and balloon fall? Watch them closely.
お盆と風船が どう落ちるのか よ～く見ておいて下さいね｡
Let's go. One, two...
いきますよ｡ せ～の｡
Did you get it? Let's look at it once more.
分かりましたか？ もう一度 見てみましょう｡
♪ ～
♪ ～
So. They fell together. Why do you think that is?
そう｡ いっしょに落ちました｡ なぜでしょうか？
Without the platter, the baloon falls slowly.
お盆にのせずに 風船をそのまま 落とすと ゆっくり落ちます｡
This is because there is air resistance.
それは 空気の 抵抗 があるからです｡
The platter, more than the baloon is...
お盆は 風船よりも…｡
From here on let's think for ourselves.
ここから先は 自分で考えよう｡
From here on we're all thinking crows.
これからは みんなが 考えるｶﾗｽ｡